<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <info><author>
            <personname>AllKind</personname>
            <email>AllKind@fastest.cc</email>
            <personblurb>
                <para>Some guy infront of a screen.</para>
            </personblurb>
            <uri type="homepage">
                <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    ns1:href="http://sf.net/projects/ip-array"> http://sf.net/projects/ip-array
                </link>
            </uri>
            <contrib>Thanks go to the open source community.</contrib>
        </author>
        <productname>ip-array</productname>
        <productnumber>1.0</productnumber>
    </info>
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>ip-array</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
        <refmiscinfo class="manual">ip-array 1.0</refmiscinfo>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
        <refdescriptor>ip-array</refdescriptor>
        <refname>ip-array</refname>
        <refpurpose>Firewall and Traffic control Configuration utility</refpurpose>
        <refclass> Scope = security, networking, system administration -- <application
                class="software">linux - </application>
            <application class="software">netfilter/iptables - </application>
            <application class="software">tc</application>
        </refclass>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>ip-array</command>
            <arg choice="plain">parameter</arg>
            <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">
                <replaceable>option</replaceable>
                <arg choice="opt">
                    <replaceable>option_argument</replaceable>
                </arg>
            </arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsect1>
        <title>Description</title>
        <para> ip-array is a command generator for netfilter (currently only iptables), tc, /proc
            filesystem and kernel module configuration. </para>
        <para> It is written in bash. Bash version 3.1 or higher is required. </para>
        <para> Basic configuration is done via shell style configuration files. Rules are defined
            using a simple XML syntax. The XML configuration files get converted to bash scripts,
            which are read at runtime. </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>Parameters</title>
        <para> If the first parameter is omitted, usage instructions are printed. Only one parameter
            is allowed - but required - for ip-array to take any action. </para>
        <para xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
            >These parameters control the 'mode' IP-Array runs on.</para>
        <itemizedlist xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <listitem>
                <para>start</para>
                <para>All network connections are forbidden (see lockdown mode below) until all
                    configuration has been read. Module probing (if configured) is done first. After
                    all commands are compiled, they are applied at once. An iptables rule listing is
                    saved for later difference checks.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>stop</para>
                <para>All tables and chains and ipset sets get flushed and destroyed. All tc qdisc
                    are removed, no traffic shaping is active any more. Modules configured to be
                    loaded are removed.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>restart</para>
                <para>Module probing (if configured) is done first. After all commands are compiled,
                    they are applied at once. An iptables rule listing is saved for later difference
                    checks.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>test</para>
                <para>Acts like the 'restart', but will use the testing configuration below the
                    'test' folder. Also it will schedule a restore job (using the `at' command
                    scheduler) for the time specified with <varname>RELOAD_TIME</varname> in the
                    defaults file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>open</para>
                <para>Module probing (if configured) is done first.</para>
                <para>This mode leaves only the NAT rules active (reads configuration and re-applies
                    them), all other tables are emptied. Policies are set to ACCEPT. An iptables
                    rule listing is saved for later difference checks. The ipset ruleset will not be
                    touched.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>tc-start</para>
                <para>Start traffic shaping only. Mangle table rules will be (re)-applied. An
                    iptables rule listing is saved for later difference checks.  ipset ruleset will
                    not be touched.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>tc-stop</para>
                <para>Stop traffic shaping only. Mangle table rules will be (re)-applied. Qdisks of
                    interfaces listed in <varname>NET_INTERFACES</varname> will be deleted. An
                    iptables rule listing is saved for later difference checks. ipset ruleset will
                    not be touched.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>lockdown</para>
                <para>All filter table policies will be set to DROP, all others will be set to
                    ACCEPT. All chains get flushed and custom chains are deleted. No more network
                    connections are allowed except:<simplelist>
                        <member>A: If the bash environment variable SSH_CONNECTION is set, IP-Array
                            allow connections from that source address to the ssh server
                            port.</member>
                        <member>B: If the environment variable is not set, but the ADMIN_CONNECTION
                            variable is set in the main config file, IP-Array will allow the
                            configured connection.</member>
                        <member>C: If the ALLOW_LOOPBACK variable is set in the main config file,
                            loopback communication will be allowed.</member>
                    </simplelist></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>interactive</para>
                <para>In this mode several wizards are available to interactively create or edit the
                    IP-Array configuration. It is possible to create main configuration files,
                    templates,  rule files, or create and edit ruleblocks. The
                        <command>whiptail</command> program is required for this. The global_defs
                    configuration file holds 3 variables (<varname>IACTIVE_WINDOW_HEIGHT</varname>,
                        <varname>IACTIVE_WINDOW_WITH</varname>,
                        <varname>IACTIVE_LIST_HEIGHT</varname>) for configuring the sizes of the
                    wizards dialog boxes. By default they are set to `0'. If this is kept and the
                        <command>tput</command> program is available in PATH, it will used to query
                    and set the required values for window height, window with and list height.
                    Otherwise it is possible to adjust the window settings there, with the downside
                    of having static values.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>diff-last-activated</para>
                <para>Every time IP-Array is not in 'test' mode and activates an iptables ruleset,
                    it saves a listing of the rules to a file. Using this parameter a (simple
                        <filename>diff</filename> based) difference check between the currently
                    active ruleset and the listing of the file is performed. Thus allowing to detect
                    (unwanted) modifications.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>dry-run</para>
                <para>Configuration is processed and validated, but no commands will be applied.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>save</para>
                <para>The currently active iptables and ipset ruleset will be saved using
                    `iptables-save' and `ipset save'.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>save-known-good</para>
                <para>Save the currently active ruleset to file (the name of the file can be set
                    using the variable <varname>KNOWN_GOOD_RULESET</varname> in the defaults file.
                    It will be used if <varname>RESTORE_ON_START</varname> is set to `1' (quick
                    start activated).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>restore</para>
                <para>The previously saved ruleset (using the 'save' parameter) will be restored
                    using `iptables-restore' `ipset restore'.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>save-commands</para>
                <para>Save all commands (modprobe, proc, tc, iptables, ipset) to a file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>save-iptables-commands</para>
                <para>Save the generated iptables and ipset commands to a file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>save-modprobe-commands</para>
                <para>Save the generated modprobe commands to a file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>save-proc-commands</para>
                <para>Save the generated /proc commands to a file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>save-tc-commands</para>
                <para>Save the generated tc commands to file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>save-shaping-commands</para>
                <para>Save the generated tc and iptables mangle table (mark) commands to
                    file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>prepare-restore-on-start</para>
                <para>Create the '<emphasis role="bold">quick start</emphasis>' scripts. After the
                    configuration is completed this parameter allows to save it into scripts holding
                    the compiled commands, in order to quickly (re)apply it to the system. If
                    iptables-save is used (<varname>IPTSAVE_FAILS</varname> is set to `0') the
                    currently active ruleset will be saved. The name for these 'known-good' script
                    can be set in the defaults file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>parse-xml</para>
                <para>Compile bash scripts from the XML files. By default templates, ruleblocks and
                    rules are converted. The -pb, -pr and -pt parameters allow to select which of
                    those will be compiled.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>compat-check</para>
                <para>A compatibility check will be performed. IP-Array will probe the kernel
                    version, supported iptables tables, targets and matches, available proc
                    settings, modules and programs. The result will be printed to stdout.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>show</para>
                <para>Show configuration or colour settings. The option `-sc' selects the type of
                    information to display. By default the settings of the main configuration file
                    are shown.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>version</para>
                <para>Show version information.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>help, -h, --help, -?</para>
                <para>Show usage information.</para>
                <para>If `--public-functions' is used as second argument, a list of available public
                    functions is printed. If a name of public function is given as third argument, a
                    brief description of the function is shown.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>Options</title>
        <para>All options are optional. Some require an argument, others do not. All options and
            their arguments must be separated by blank(s). If an option can be used more than once,
            it is mentioned explicitly. </para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                <listitem>
                    <para>-ct, --ipt-counters</para>
                    <para>Save or restore iptables counters when using the `save' or `restore'
                        startup parameter.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-dg, --debug</para>
                    <para>Enable debugging output.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-dr, --dry-run</para>
                    <para>Commands will not be applied.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-ex, --err-exit</para>
                    <para>Set bash to exit onsimple command failure (set -e) and to inherit the ER
                        trap to functions, etc.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-na, --no-autosave</para>
                    <para>Do not use the automatic saving and restoring logic.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-nc, --no-compat-check</para>
                    <para>Do not perform the compatibility check. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-nd, --no-diff</para>
                    <para>Do not save the diff file for the difference check of the ruleset
                        (diff-last-activated startup parameter).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-ni, --no-iface-check</para>
                    <para>Do not check for the existence of interfaces.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-nm, --no-modprobe</para>
                    <para>Do not perform load or unload kernel modules.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-np, --no-proc</para>
                    <para>Do not set the /proc filesystem configuration.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-p, --parse-xml</para>
                    <para>Read all XML files and overwrite already compiled bash scripts.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-pb, --parse-ruleblocks</para>
                    <para>Read XML ruleblock files and overwrite already compiled bash
                        scripts.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-pr, --parse-rulefiles</para>
                    <para>Read XML rule files and overwrite already compiled bash scripts.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-pt, --parse-templates</para>
                    <para>Read XML template files and overwrite already compiled bash
                        scripts.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-t, --test</para>
                    <para>Schedule the restore of the active ruleset..</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-b, --base-dir directory</para>
                    <para>Set base directory to use (i.e. /etc/ip-array).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-c, --config-file file</para>
                    <para>Specify the name of the main configuration file to use.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-C, --config-dir directory</para>
                    <para>Set directory for the main configuration file.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-d, --defaults-file full_path_to_file</para>
                    <para>Specify the full path of the defaults file to use.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-e, --exe-dir directory</para>
                    <para>Set the directory to place the main executable of IP-Array into (i.e.
                        /usr/bin/ip-array).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-l, --lib-dir directory</para>
                    <para>Set the directory to place the function file(s) of IP-Array into (i.e.
                        /usr/lib/ip-array).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-r, --run-dir directory</para>
                    <para>Set the directory to place the PID file into (i.e. /var/run).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-s, --save-file file</para>
                    <para>Specify the name of the file used to save or restore a ruleset.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-si, --save-ips-file file</para>
                    <para>Specify the name of the file used to save or restore an ipset
                        ruleset.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-co, --color 0 | 1</para>
                    <para>Enable or disable coloured output.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-ui, --use-ipset 0 | 1</para>
                    <para>Enable or disable usage of ipset. This setting is globally. It disables
                        builtin usage as well as the users ipset rules.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-o, --set-option assignment [...]</para>
                    <para>Override variables of the main configuration file. i.e. <code>-o
                            ENABLE_NAT=0</code>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-gf, --gen-format type</para>
                    <para>Generate command in iptables-save format, or as command list. Available
                        types: `cmd' (= default) or `ipt'.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-rs, --restore-on-start 0 | 1</para>
                    <para>Enable or disabe quickstart (only valid using the `start'
                        parameter).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-rt, --reload-time 1-15</para>
                    <para>Time in minutes until the saved ruleset will be restored.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-sc, --show-config [type]</para>
                    <para>Select type of information to show. If type is omitted, the settings of
                        the main configuration file will be displayed.</para>
                    <para>Available types are: <simplelist>
                            <member> all (everything will be displayed)</member>
                            <member> ansi_codes (display ANSI codes for coloured shell
                                output)</member>
                            <member> colors (available colours)</member>
                            <member> defaults[:NAME[,...] display all or just the selected variable
                                names from the defaults file.</member>
                            <member> main[:NAME[,...] display all or just the selected variable
                                names from the main configuration file file.</member>
                            <member> targets (show all available iptables targets).</member>
                            <member> matches (show all available iptables matches).</member>
                            <member> rules (show the compiled iptables rules).</member>
                            <member> ipt_args[:NAME[,...] display all or just the selected iptables
                                arguments help.</member>
                            <member> ruleblocks[:NAME[,...] display all or just the selected
                                ruleblock names.</member>
                            <member> templates[:NAME[,...] display all or just the selected
                                templates names.</member>
                            <member> proc display the /proc filesystem configuration options, paths
                                and their configured values.</member>
                            <member> public_functions[:NAME[,...] display all or just the selected
                                public functions help.</member>
                            <member> find_templates:template-entry-glob[,...] find templates
                                containing all entries of the comma separated search list.</member>
                        </simplelist></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-sh, --shell /path/shell</para>
                    <para>Specify an alternative shell to run IP-Array.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-sv, --syslog-verbose 0-6</para>
                    <para>Specify the level of output verbosity to syslog. Allowed values are from
                        `0' to `6'. Overrides the value of <varname>SYSLOG_VERBOSE</varname> in the
                        defaults file.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>-v, --verbose 0-9</para>
                    <para>Specify the level of output verbosity. Allowed values are from `0' to `9'.
                        Overrides the value of <varname>VERBOSE</varname> in the defaults
                        file.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>Environment</title>
        <para> If the environment variable <varname>DEBUG_INFO</varname> is set, additional
            debugging information is displayed. If in addition the output verbosity is set to
                <option>8</option> or higher, a debugging <varname>PS4</varname> is set. </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>Exit status</title>
        <para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>0</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Success </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>1</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Undetermined error. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>3</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Usage error. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>111</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Requested item (file, folder) does not exist error. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>112</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Item (configuration variable) not defined error. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>113</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Failed loading item (script, program) error. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>114</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> General fail condition error. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>115</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Configuration error. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>Files</title>
        <para>
            <filename>/usr/bin/ip-array</filename>
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>See also</title>
        <para>
            <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>ip-array_defaults.conf</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>ip-array.conf</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>ip-array_ruleblocks</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>ip-array_rulefiles</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>ip-array_templates</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>
        </para>
        <para>
            <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>iptables</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>iptables-save</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>iptables-restore</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>tc</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>tc-htb</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>, <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>tc-sfq</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>
        </para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>
